<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Grieving of Gods spirit Contayning the summe of a sermon preached at Saint Maries in Oxford. The chiefe points intreated on are, Viz. I. Of grieuing of Gods Spirit. II. Of resisting of Gods Spirit. III. Of blaspheming of Gods Spirit, in the highest degree commonly called, the sinne against the Holy Ghost. By Radford Mauericke, minister in Devon. Reade iudiciously, but iudge charitably.</title>
            <author>Mavericke, Radford, b. 1560 or 61.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17681</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102313</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838102</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838102</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2461</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07286)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2461)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1074:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Grieving of Gods spirit Contayning the summe of a sermon preached at Saint Maries in Oxford. The chiefe points intreated on are, Viz. I. Of grieuing of Gods Spirit. II. Of resisting of Gods Spirit. III. Of blaspheming of Gods Spirit, in the highest degree commonly called, the sinne against the Holy Ghost. By Radford Mauericke, minister in Devon. Reade iudiciously, but iudge charitably.</title>
                  <author>Mavericke, Radford, b. 1560 or 61.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; trimmed at head, affecting running title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2461:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2461:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GRIEVING OF GODS SPIRIT.</p>
            <p>Contayning the ſumme of a Sermon preached at Saint <hi>MARIES</hi> in OXFORD.</p>
            <p>The chiefe points intreated on are, Viz.
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>Of grieuing of Gods Spirit.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>Of reſiſting of Gods Spirit.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>Of blaſpheming of Gods Spirit, in the highest degree commonly called, The ſinne against the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Radford Mauericke,</hi> Miniſter in DEVON.</p>
            <p>Reade iudiciouſly, but iudge charitably.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATTH. 7.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
For, with what Iudgement ye iudge, ye ſhall be iudged, and with what meaſure ye mete, it ſhall be meaſured to you againe.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Stansby.</hi> 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:2461:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2461:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND FATHER IN GOD, GEORGE Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterburie</hi> his Grace, Primate of all <hi>England,</hi> and Metropolitane; <hi>And one of his Maieſties moſt Honourable Priuie</hi> Councell: All ſauing graces, wiſhed in this life, and all during Glorie in the life to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MOST REVEREND,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow much the Miniſters of the Goſpell within your Graces Prouince, haue and doe continually reioyce of your preferment to this place, and how many zealous Prayers are made vnto God, for your Graces long and happie continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance therein, I the least, and one of the lowest among them, can partly report: But my purpoſe is not to prayſe, but in all humilitie to pray your Grace, ſo farre to bee pleaſed, as to permit with your accuſtomed fauour, This poore Mite, of a Miniſters good meaning, to be cast into the rich Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie of our Engliſh Church; And with more ſpeciall
<pb facs="tcp:2461:3"/>regard, to ſuffer theſe two first Sermons, preached long ſithence in your Graces preſence, to paſſe vnder the wings of your fauourable protection, being not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imboldned hereunto by your Graces late remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of them, but euen incouraged to publiſh them in print, which the importunitie of ſome this long time could hardly gaine at my hands.</p>
            <p>But now old age hauing taken hold on mee, and my ſelfe hauing no children, by naturall generation, I haue thought it meet to collect together, into one Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, or Continent, my little Babes or Bookes, which yet wander abroad in the wide World, ſingle by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; with ſuch other, as my little leiſure, and leſſe learning could bring forth, to keepe them companie: hoping they may yeeld me ſome comfort, in the ſhutting up of my dayes, aſwell as profit others (if pleaſe God) ſo long as this day of ſaluation laſteth.</p>
            <p>Thus commending my poore endeuours to Gods rich bleſsing, and your worthy Grace, to Gods gracious protection; with bended knees, I most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly take my leaue; and euer remaine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces, in all humble dutie at command, RAFFORD MAVERICKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:2461:3"/>
            <head>THE GRIEVING OF GODS SPIRIT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EPHES. 4.30.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Grieue not the holy Spirit of God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much (Men,
<note place="margin">Exordium.</note> Brethren and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) as this ſentence is allowed off, <hi>Verbum ſapienti ſat est,</hi> I ſhould much forget my ſelfe, If I did not well conſider, as before whom I ſpeake, the ſupremeſt Maieſtie, ſo vnto whom, as graue, learned, and iudcious Auditorie (as <hi>England</hi> or all <hi>Europe</hi> yeeldeth.)</p>
            <p>The conſideration whereof (I thanke God) doth much comfort, but not diſcourage me at all; for ſpeaking before God, his diuine Grace being implored, ſhall (I truſt) guide and direct mee, to ſpeake as of the Word of God; And ſpeaking vnto iudicious but charitable hearers, they will rather conceiue what I meane, if deſire of breuitie, cauſe any obſcuritie in my ſpeech; rather then raſhly condemne any thing that ſhall be ſpoken, ſo that it be not againſt the grounds of Learning or Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2461:4"/>Leauing therefore to hinder your attention, from the matter intended, we will, (God-willing) proceed on with our Text, Contayning a very graue dehortation, of a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſome great conſequence, or importance, which may be dilated on, without any diuiſion at all, Conſiſting as it were but of one particular branch, or member: howbeit for orders ſake, and for the better helpe of memorie, (for, <hi>Confuſio eſt &amp; intelligeutiae,
<note place="margin">Three parts of this Sermon.</note> &amp; memoriae, inimica</hi>) I haue purpoſed to purſue this Text, in this manner.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> by ſhewing what is meant by grieuing of Gods Spirit; and who they are that properly may bee ſayd to grieue the holy Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſeeing, reſiſting of Gods Spirit, is a greater ſinne, then grieuing of Gods Spirit, we will (God aſſiſting) ſpeake of that point in the next place.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> for as much as blaſpheming of Gods Spirit, is a ſinne (reuealed vnto vs in the Scripture,) farre greater then either of the two former, we will endeuour by Gods grace, and with your learned patience, to ſpeake thereof in the third place.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Grieue not the holy Spirit, of God.</head>
               <p>TO grieue the Spirit of God,
<note place="margin">The firſt part. What is meant by grieuing of Gods Spirit.</note> is a figuratiue phraſe, or ſpeech <hi>(humanitus dictum)</hi> ſpoken for mans capacity, for truly and indeed the Spirit of God, as God himſelfe, can be no more grieued, then hee can be either wounded or killed; but this phraſe of ſpeech is here vſed by our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, to aggrauate the greatneſſe of ſinne, ſeeing by ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, we doe as much as in vs lyeth, euen grieue the holy Spirit of God, that is, grieuouſly offend Gods Spirit, whoſe ſpeciall office is to worke ſanctification in the harts of Gods Children.</p>
               <p>This ſpeech therefore is not vſed, as one very well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth, <hi>Quod vllam perturbationem ſentiat diuinitas, ſed vt indignitatem prophana vitae, magis intelligamus.</hi> It is not ſpoken (I ſay) to make vs imagine, That the diuine Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is, or can bee ſubiect to any perturbation, but to
<pb facs="tcp:2461:4"/>make vs the more and more to conceiue the indignitie, and vileneſſe of ſinne; and how odious ſinne is, in the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>The ſimilitude of this ſpeech,
<note place="margin">A Simile.</note> may ſeeme to bee bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from a honeſt Oaſt, that hath receiued a good Cheſt into his houſe, to whome for a while he hath giuen very good entertainment, but ſoone after, forgetting both his owne credit, and his Cheſts comfort, ſuffereth wittingly and willingly, many diſorders to be committed in his houſe, to the great griefe and diſcontent of that Cheſt, which at the firſt was ſo courteouſly intertained; by meanes whereof the good Gheſt, doth ſeeme to make of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that he will forſake his lodge, and ſeeke a new Oaſt, ſauing that his gentle nature is ſuch, that hee euery day hopeth, and expecteth, (as he is oftentimes promiſed) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and amendment of all that is amiſſe.</p>
               <p>Right ſo it falleth out, betweene Gods Spirit and a Chriſtian man,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19.</note> who in the Scripture is called <hi>The Temple of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> This holy and bleſſed Spirit as the good Gheſt, doth with the Hammer of Gods Word, knock at the doore of our hearts to ſeeke entertainment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold, I ſtand</hi> (ſaith the Spirit) <hi>at the doore and knock,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Renel.</hi> 3.20.</note> If any man heare my voyce, and open the doore</hi> (for there be many that heare his voice who will not open the doore) <hi>I will come into him, and ſup with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now when any faithfull Chriſtian, hath thus receiued this good Gheſt, and giuen him entertainment to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ſoone after forgetting both himſelfe and this his Cheſt, he ſuffers other vnruly Gheſts, which were in that houſe, before this good Gheſt came thither, (the luſts and affections of the fleſh I meane) to beare rule, and to keepe a ſtirre in that houſe, to commit many ſhamefull and vngodly prankes, by meanes whereof the good Gheſt, the good Spirit of God, is not onely diſquieted and troubled, but letted and hindred, from doing that good which he came to doe; being woarie as it ware to tanie any longer in that Houſe or Iune, and therefore
<pb facs="tcp:2461:5"/>ſometimes doth hide himſelfe cloſe in ſome corner of that Houſe, like fire couered in the Embers, or aſhes, not making any comfortable meale, with his Oaſt in many dayes and weekes together.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.12</note> And if the diſorders be verie great, ſuch as the Adulterie and Murther of <hi>Dauid</hi> were, he will hardly be found out in a whole yeere together; ſo greatly is this good Gheſt, this holy Spirit of God, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and diſpleaſed with ſinne, or at leaſt ſo odious and offenſiue is ſinne in his ſight.</p>
               <p>Nay (which more is) many times he will not be found out at all, before euery corner of our hearts, ſoules and conſciences bee cleane waſhed with bitter teares of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and theſe vnruly affections, which made all the former diſorders, be in ſome ſort tamed and ſubdued, yea and vntill the Oaſt himſelfe who ſuffered theſe parts to be played, be ſeuerely puniſhed in the Houſe of GODS correction,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.38.</note> where hee muſt daily waſh his wounds with the water of contrition; As <hi>Dauid waſhed his Couch with teares,</hi> as <hi>Mary Magdalene waſhed the feet of Christ,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.75. What it is to grieue the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit of God.</note> and as <hi>Peter went out and wept bitterly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this ſimilitude ſo opened and explayned, the verie ſimplieſt I ſuppoſe, may ſoone perceiue, what it is to grieue the holy Spirit of God, namely, after that by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>of</hi> Gods Word, wee haue receiued Faith, and in ſome meaſure the ſanctifying Spirit of God, and haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained him with ioy and gladneſſe; yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, many times and often, through to too much ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, careleſneſſe and negligence, and ſometimes through bold preſumption, and wilfull wickedneſſe, we ſuffer the vnruly luſts of the fleſh, to ſway and to beare rule in vs, ſo long, till as length we breake out into groſſe ſinnes and enormities, whereby wee doe euen grieue the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, or as our Apoſtle ſeemes to expound himſelfe in another place,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee doe quench the Spirit of God, and as much as in vs lyeth, labour to extinguiſh and cleane put one the fire of Gods Grace, with the cold water of ſinne and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe,</hi> which water of wickedneſſe, if it bee not in
<pb facs="tcp:2461:5"/>time dryed vp againe, by Faith and true Repentance (as it is euermore in the elect Children of God) it would needs drowne our ſoules, in that bottomleſſe pit of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               <p>The vſe then that we ſhould make hereof is this,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> That learning hereby the deteſtation that God hath againſt ſinne, we ſhould alwaies feare to commit it, and therefore ſhould make a conſcience of euery ſinne, ſuch ſinnes, as we account common ſinnes, and the Papiſts call veniall ſinnes, neuer weighing ſinne in the ballance of our ſinfull conceit, but with the true waights of the Lords Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and according to the account that God makes of it, aſſuring our ſelues that euery ſinne in its owne nature, though neuer ſo ſmall in our ſenſe, being committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an infinite God, doth iuſtly deſerue an infinite pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, the ignorance whereof, cauſeth ſo little conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſinning, and ſo great prophaneneſſe to be in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chriſtians, as is now to bee ſeene euery-where, by meanes whereof, they doe as our Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Constrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſpiritum, Grieue the holy Spirit,</hi> and as one well noteth vpon that place, <hi>quaſi ex ſuo hospitio eum eijcimus, euen caſt him out of his owne habitation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe, wee are here taught,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> how ſweete and pleaſing a thing it is to the holy Spirit of God that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in vs, and to his holy Angels, that watch and ward round about vs, to liue and leade a holy life and godly conuerſation: For if ſinne and vngodlineſſe, doe ſo grieue and offend the Spirit of God as ſurely it doth, though we cannot conceiue the manner how, then doubtleſſe vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and holy liuing, are moſt pleaſing to the ſame Spirit. And as the holy Spirit of God will not dwell in a ſoule ſubiected to ſin, ſo hee dwelleth with great delight and content in that ſoule which is ſanctified by grace.</p>
               <p>Therefore it is well ſaid of one, <hi>Oportet nos operam dare, vt ſpiritus ſanctus, libenter in nobis habitet, vt in domicilio laeto ac iucundo nec vlla tristitiae materia illi detur.</hi> That it behooueth all Chriſtians to giue all diligence ſo to liue,
<pb facs="tcp:2461:6"/>as the holy Spirit of God may take delight for to dwell and remaine in vs, as in a moſt pleaſant Pauilion; and that no cauſe of griefe be giuen vnto him through our careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and continuall cuſtome of ſinning. So ſhould it come to paſſe, that as God takes delight in vs, ſo ſhould we haue comfort in him, he through our holy obedience, and wee through peace of conſcience to our endleſſe ioy and conſolation.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee, what it is to grieue the holy Spirit of God in our ſelues, or to quench the good gifts and graces of Gods holy Spirit within vs; which ſinne, I take to bee proper to Gods Saints and Children; and therefore thinke it good to diſtinguiſh the three ſinnes before named, that is, <hi>Grieuing, Reſiſting, and Blaſpheming of God Spirit;</hi> in this manner.</p>
               <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I ſay to grieue the holy Spirit of God, or to quench the Spirit, is a ſinne of Gods Children, who by the preaching of Gods Word, and inward working of Gods Grace, haue receiued Faith, and in ſome meaſure the ſanctifying Spirit of God before: which Spirit of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, is giuen to none in that manner or meaſure, but only to Gods Elect; nor neuer taken vtterly from any to whom it is once giuen. <hi>For thoſe whom God once loueth, to the end he loueth them.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29.</note> And the gifts and calling of God are without Repentance.</hi> Therefore it is obſerued in King <hi>Dauid,</hi> after his fearefull falls, <hi>That he prayes to haue this holy ſpirit renewed within him:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.10.</note> hauing layen ſtill as it were a while without any comfortable motion, but was neuer vtterly taken from him. And this note I giue by the way the rather leſt any of Gods Children, that are to too much caſt downe alreadie, with the feeling of their ſinnes, ſhoul be ouer-whelmed with too much heauineſſe: as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to teach, that they may bee daily renewed by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, for their daily relictions, contrarie to that old He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie of the <hi>Nouatians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Nouatian</hi> Hereſie.</note> which held the contrarie. For though to grieue the Spirit of God by ſinning, bee a great aggrauating of ſinne, yet being many times, the ſinne of
<pb facs="tcp:2461:6"/>Gods Elect Children, it is pardoned and forgiuen in Chriſt; And albeit ſome haue thought that thoſe places of Scriptue in the ſixt and tenth to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> haue poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at this ſinne, of grieuing of Gods Spirit;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. &amp; 10.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore could not bee renewed by Repentance, yet it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that in thoſe places That great ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt is touched vpon, whereof wee haue promiſed and purpoſe God-willing to ſpeake in its owne place. I ſay therefore, for the comfort of the godly afflicted in conſcience, but to flatter none in their ſinnes, That to grieue the holy Spirit of God, or ſometimes by ſinning to quench as it were the good gifts and graces of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is a ſinne oftentimes committed by the Children of God, that are called by the preaching of the Goſpell, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by Faith, and in ſome meaſure ſanctified by the holy Spirit of God, this I ſay is the ſinne many times of Gods Children, againſt which ſinne, as againſt all ſinne, they doe much labour and ſtriue, and daily, yea, almoſt hourely they doe repent for the ſame.</p>
               <p>To reſiſt the Spirit of God, being the ſecond pont,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> I haue propoſed to ſpeake off, is the proper ſinne of ſuch as are not yet effectually called, nor ſanctifyed, but may be in time, if God giue them grace, to repent and beleeue the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>But to blaſpheme the Spirit of God in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, which is called the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is onely that ſin, which cannot be renewed by Repentance. And ſo much for grieuing of Gods Spirit in our ſelues, and of the difference betwixt grieuing, reſiſting, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Gods Spirit.</p>
               <p>Now there is moreouer,
<note place="margin">A ſecond ſort of Greiuers of Gods Spirit.</note> another ſort of grieuers of Gods Spirit, but not in themſelues, but in others and theſe are farre different, from the former, and without ſpeedie Repentance, may come neere to the latter: Such were many ſinfull ſinners of the olde World, who did grieue the holy Spirit of God which was in <hi>Noah;</hi> and ſuch as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith <hi>vexed iuſt Lot,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 27.</note> with their vncleanly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation:</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2461:7"/>And ſuch as grieued Saint <hi>Paul</hi> when hee ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Many walke of whom I haue told you often and now tell you weeping;</hi> And ſuch as <hi>Dauid</hi> complayned of, when hee ſaid, <hi>Mine eyes guſh out with teares becauſe men keepe not Gods Law.</hi> Such grieuers of Gods Spirit in others, wee haue but too too many in our dayes, and this Age is full of ſuch vngodly perſons, which take pleaſure to mocke and ſcoffe at all vertuous and godly exerciſes in others, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king but a paſt-time of ſinne in themſelues, and the more they are reproued, the more ſinfull they are, and the more outragiouſly they runne into all miſchiefe, to the high diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honouring of Almightie God, euen in contempt of God and all goodneſſe, to the diſgrace of Chriſtianitie, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to the great griefe of the godly, ſpecially of thoſe, who haue the cure and charge of their ſoules committed vnto them.</p>
               <p>But for ſo much as thoſe grieuers of Gods Spirit in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, doe reſiſt the ſame Spirit of God againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, wee will here conclude our firſt propoſed part of grieuing of Gods Spirit, and ſo come to the next, to ſhew what it is, and who they are, that doe reſiſt the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, obſeruing this not by the way, that GODS Spirit is called the holy Spirit of God, not becauſe hee is holier then either the Father or the Sonne, but becauſe his proper office is, to ſanctifie and to make holy the Elect Children of God.</p>
               <p>So come we now to ſpeake of <hi>Reſisting of Gods Spirit,</hi> being the ſecond generall part of our Text.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>TO reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">The ſecond part of this Sermon, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of Gods Spirit.</note> is on the one ſide, to deſpiſe, or to make little account of the good gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Gods Spirit, and of thoſe good meanes, which God hath appointed to bring vs vnto Saluation. As the deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Gods Word, Sacraments, and Prayer, prophaning of the Lords Sabbaths which he hath ſanctified, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ordained for holy exerciſes, to mocke or ieſt at the preaching of the Word, and of the Preachers thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2461:7"/>Theſe are great ſinnes, and to bee repented off aboue many other ſinnes, becauſe they manifeſtly fight againſt the firſt Table of Gods Law, and againſt the whole wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Seruice of God.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, to reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt, is to harden our hearts, and to ſtop the eares of our ſoules againſt the Word of God, (as ſome Recuſants will ſtop the eares of their bodies with Wooll, when ſome inforcement bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them to Church) <hi>To day,</hi> ſaith the Holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.7.</note> 
                  <hi>if you will heare my voyce, harden not your hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was the ſinne of the Iſraelites, in the Wilderneſſe, when God proued them fortie yeeres, whether they would obey him, and heare his voyce, but they would not, at length God ſware vnto them in his wrath, that they ſhould not enter into his reſt, that was into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But behold a fearfull Iudgement of God, of ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand (no ſmall number) there were onely two perſons, <hi>Caleb,</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.30.</note> that entred into that Land of Promiſe, The reſt were ouerthrowne in the Wilderneſſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> are examples vnto vs,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6.</note> and are written to admoniſh vs, vpon whome the ends of the World are come. That wee ſhould not luſt after euill things, as they luſted, nor tempt God, as they tempted him; nor murmur, as they murmured, nor harden our hearts againſt the Word of God, as they did, leſt the Lord ſware in his wrath, as he did vnto them, that wee ſhould neuer enter into his eternall reſt, the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
               <p>Yet ſurely, this is the great and grieuous ſin of too too many in our Land, The hardning of their hearts againſt the voyce of God as the <hi>Iewes</hi> did in <hi>Ieremies</hi> time,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 18.28.</note> to whom they ſaid, <hi>Let vs not giue eare to any of his words.</hi> Let the Law and Curſe of Gods Iudgements, by the mouth of Gods Miniſters bee thundred againſt obſtinate and rebellious Sinners neuer ſo terribly, nay, let God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe thunder from Heauen neuer ſo hard and fearefully, let
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2461:8"/>fire and flaſhes of Lightning flye ouer them and vpon them. Let Houſes, Townes, and Villages with extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie fire be quite burned into aſhes, let Warre, Famine, Plagues, and Peſtilences purſue vs and almoſt ouer-take vs; Let ſome of this wicked ſort eſcape theſe or any other Iudgements of God but one inch, they'l care for no more, their hearts ſhall neuer be the ſofter, nor yet their liues one whit the better.</p>
               <p>They will be as ſinfull as euer they were, as vnmercifull as euer they were, as full of malice and diſdaine as euer they were, as hard-hearted as euer they were, and will not ſticke to ſay, <hi>Tuſh theſe things ſhall neuer come neere vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the othe otherſide, let the glad tydings of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell be preached vnto them, neuer ſo often and ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably, let the ſweet Mercies of God in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt, be offered vnto them neuer ſo freely, let the windowes of Heauen be ſet wide open, not fortie dayes, but twice fortie yeeres, and all the Bleſſings of God bee powred downe vpon them neuer ſo bountifully, yet there will no remorſe of conſcience mooue them, to conſider as they ought, of theſe innumerable benefits of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon them.</p>
               <p>And what is the cauſe of all this deadneſſe and dulneſſe in them, is it not the hardning of their hearts, againſt the Word of God? whereby they doe as much as in them lyeth, reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt, in contemning and deſpiſing thoſe good gifts and graces, which he offereth vnto them.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, it may not vnfitly bee ſaid vnto many of them, as bleſſed <hi>Steuen</hi> ſaid vnto the <hi>Iewes, Ye haue alwayes reſisted the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51.</note> But take they heed, this ſinne as I ſaid is a great ſinne, and if it bee continued in, without Repentance, a very fearefull ſinne, and ſuch a ſinne, as from whence they may aſcend, or rather deſcend (for in ſinning wee rather deſcend then aſcend) vnto the higheſt degree of ſinning which is the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>Of which ſinne, (comming now to our laſt point or
<pb facs="tcp:2461:8"/>part) that I may ſpeake truly, religiouſly, and ſoundly, I moſt humbly beſſech the moſt holy and bleſſed Spirit of God, to guide me with his grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THe ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">The third part of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>viz.</hi> of Blaſpheming of Gods Spirit <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.31. <hi>Marke</hi> 3.28. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.10.</note> is that kind of ſinne or blaſphemie, whereof our Sauiour ſpeaketh plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his Goſpell, and is recorded at large by three Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts: <hi>Matthew</hi> brings in our Sauiour ſaying, <hi>But I ſay you, Euery ſinne and and blaſphemie, ſhall bee forgiuen vnto men, but the blaſphemie against the Holy Ghoſt, ſhall not be forgiuen vnto men. And whoſoeuer ſhall ſpeake a word againſt the Sonne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f man, it ſhall be forgiuen him, but whoſoeuer ſhall ſpeake againſt the Holy Ghoſt, ſhall not be forgiuen, neither in this World, neither in the World to come:</hi> that is, as Saint <hi>Marke</hi> ſaith, <hi>ſhall be culpable of eternall damnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here then there are two things to be noted out of this Text, and generally to be obſerued in this Diſcourſe.
<note place="margin">Two Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt is, that there are many kind of Blaſphemies.</p>
               <p>Secondly, what is the greateſt, with the reaſon thereof.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>That there are many ſorts or kinds of Blaſphemies,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth plainly in that Chriſt ſaith,
<note place="margin">Many kinds of Blaſphemies.</note> Euery Sinne or Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie; ſo that in a generalitie wee may ſay, there is Blaſphemie againſt God, and Blaſphemie againſt men, created after the Image of God.</p>
               <p>Blaſphemie againſt men, as againſt Magiſtrates, againſt Parents, againſt good men, and againſt the whole Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Magiſtrates and Parents are blaſphemed, not onely when they are not obeyed and honoured as they ſhould; but alſo rather when they are ſlandered, curſed, or euill ſpoken off.</p>
               <p>It is written in the Law,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thouſhalt not ſpeake euill of the Ruler of the people.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.17.</note> He that curſeth Father or Mother, ſhall dye the death,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Good men in particular, or the whole Church in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, are blaſphemed:</p>
               <p>The whole Church in generall, When ſhee is called, the
<pb facs="tcp:2461:9"/>vngodly Syuagogue, impious, fooliſh, ſeditious, ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious or the like.</p>
               <p>The Saints either liuing or dead may bee blaſphemed, when they are called Seducers, Diſturbers, Schiſmatikes, Heretikes, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Blaſphemie againſt God, may be,</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Againſt the Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againſt the Perſon of the Sonne.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>God the Father is blaſphemed many wayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> When that which is due to the Creator is giuen to the Creature, as dinine worſhip (as well that which is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) remiſſion of ſinnes, and when falſe gods, and Superſtition, is preferred before the true God, and true Religion.</p>
               <p>This was the ſinne of the <hi>Phariſies,</hi> and now of the <hi>Papists;</hi> therefore that Beaſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> is marked and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the <hi>Renelation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 13.1.</note> with the Name of <hi>Blaſphemie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> God the Father is blaſphemed, when any ſhall doubt of his Power, or ſuppoſe any impotencie to be in God, or any inabilitie, to performe any thing that pleaſeth him, or that he hath promiſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shall God promiſe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Numb</hi> 23.19.</note> and not performe? Hath hee ſpoken, and ſhall he not accompliſh it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is the arme of the Lord ſhortned;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay</hi> 59.1.</note> that it cannot helpe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſinne, in the Wilderneſſe; <hi>Can God prouide fleſh and bread for his people?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.20.</note> It was the ſinne of that Noble man in <hi>Samaria,</hi> Who ſaid (after the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet had propheſied of that plentie of Come) <hi>Though the Lord would make windowes in the Heauens,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 7.2.</note> could this thing come to paſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, God the Father may be blaſphemed, when any are brought into ſo great extremitie, that they fall into Curſing and Blaſpheming of the Name of God; This was the ſinne that the fooliſh Wife of <hi>Iob</hi> perſwaded her Husband to commit,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Curſe God, and dye.</hi> For though the word <hi>(Curſe)</hi> in the originall doe ſignifie ſometimes to
<pb facs="tcp:2461:9"/>bleſſe, yet <hi>Iobs</hi> reprooſe of his Wife doth argue, that ſhe meant it in the worſe ſenſe.</p>
               <p>So much for blaſpheming againſt God the Father.</p>
               <p>Next, the Sonne of God,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> was alſo oftentimes blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when he was here on Earth by the <hi>Iewes,</hi> but of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them no doubt ignorantly, not knowing that hee was the Sonne of God.</p>
               <p>This Blaſphemie againſt the Sonne of God, is as if one ſhould ſee the Kings eldeſt Sonne and Heire apparant to the Crowne, clothed in poore and vile ragges, and not knowing who hee is, ſhould call him beggerly Rogue or the like, this is blaſphemie againſt the Kings Sonne, but is pardonable, becauſe it proceeded of ignorance.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Paul,</hi> or rather <hi>Saul,</hi> was a Perſecuter, and a Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer of Chriſt and his Church, but found pardon, for that hee did it ignorantly, as himſelfe coufeſſeth.</p>
               <p>For this cauſe Chriſt prayed for ſome of his Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, <hi>Father, forgiue them, for they know not what they doe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith vnto ſome of the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 23.34. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.17.</note> that crucified the Lord of life, <hi>I know, Brethren, that through ignorance ye did it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now come wee to ſpeake of Blaſphemie againſt the Holy Ghoſt, wherein wee muſt firſt obſerue,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <hi>That euery ſinne or Blaſphemie, against the Spirit of God, is not that ſinne againſt the Holy Ghost, which ſhall neuer bee forgiuen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As namely, <hi>griouing, quenching, and reſisting of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost,</hi> (whereof wee haue ſpoken) though they are great ſinnes, and ſome of them farre greater then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet are they ſuch ſinnes as are and haue beene pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, therefore none of them are that ſinne, which wee call, <hi>The ſinne againſt the Holy Ghost.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer, there are greater ſinnes then theſe, as deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God or his knowne Truth, through feare or any other infirmitie: Alſo perſecuting of Gods Church and Children, through ignorance, yet neither of theſe is that ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, though they bee very feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſinnes, ſeeing they haue been committed by GODS
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2461:10"/>owne Seruants, and alſo pardoned vnto them; Example we haue of the one in <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 22.61. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</note> of the other in <hi>Paul,</hi> both great Apoſtles of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>By this negation or oppoſition, <hi>What ſinnes are not that ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> we ſhall, I truſt, the better conſider, and ſooner find out, what this peculiar ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt is; whereof we are now (God aſſiſting vs) punctually to intreate.
<note place="margin">Two cauſes why the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt ſhould bee made knowne.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And ſeeing it is ſo great a ſinne, yea, the greateſt ſinne; and ſuch a ſinne, as ſhall not be forgiuen, it is moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie that it ſhould be diſtinguiſhed, and made knowne from all other ſinnes, and that for two cauſes eſpecially.</p>
               <p>The one to this end,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that we knowing the danger ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſhould euermore moſt carefully flye farre off from ſo deepe Pit of perdition.</p>
               <p>The other,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>(which in my opinion is the beſt vſe that may be made now in this time of peace and fun-ſhine of the Goſpell) to make knowne vnto Gods people, yea, euen vnto them which are more ſimple, leſt Satan ſhould make any to beleeue or thinke, who being fallen or ſlyding into ſome other Pit of ſinne, neere or ſomewhat like vnto this; That they are plunged in this deepe Gulfe of perdition, neuer more to be recouered. For as we muſt not be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of Satans ſlights, (as the Apoſtle ſaith) ſo muſt Chriſt his Miniſters aboue all other bee as carefull, and readie to preuent him, and to inſtruct Gods Children, in all ſuch points of ſound doctrine, as are required, either for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort or inſtruction.</p>
               <p>Wherefore in my poore vnderſtanding, they are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in this particular to be blamed, who though they will not ſpeake againſt preaching in generall, yet will they by no meanes allow all the Doctrine reuealed in the Word of God, to bee taught and preached vnto the people of God.</p>
               <p>Some ſay, that <hi>Predestination</hi> (being a chiefe, if not the chiefeſt point in all Diuinitie) ought rather to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed, then publikely to bee taught and preached vnto the people.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2461:10"/>Others hold, (and theſe are <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſpecially) that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſentences of Scripture, (which indeed are moſt ſweete to repentant and ſorrowfull ſinners) as, <hi>At what time ſoeuer a Sinner doth repent,</hi> and the like, are vnfit to be either read or preached to the people, for feare (forſooth) leſt ſome will take thereupon the more libertie of ſinning, as though becauſe Grace doth abound, therefore ſin ſhould abound which is onely the fault of graceleſſe perſons, but neuer of any of Gods Children.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, many are of opinion, that this ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, is not at all to bee defined, at leaſt not to be declared or ſpoken of in publike.</p>
               <p>I grant (Reuerend Fathers) that theſe, as all other points of Diuinitie, and ſome of theſe, aboue many other points of Diuinitie, ought very religiouſly, and diſcreetly, to be taught and preached vnto the people: but to hold opinion, or to labour to maintayne it which is worſe, that any of theſe or other like points of Doctrine muſt bee concealed, which God of purpoſe hath declared in his Word, to be opened and reuealed, is ſarre from all Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, (to ſpeake the beſt of it) and nothing agreeing with the rule and practice of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 20.35.</note> that great Doctor of vs Gentiles, Who boaſted and tooke exceeding comfort thereby vnto himſelfe, that he had reuealed to his Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie at times, All the Councell of God; that is, not all that God hath or doth keepe ſecret to himſelfe, but all that God hath or had reuealed vnto the Apoſtle, either o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly in his Word, or by any ſecret Reuelation from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which points ſo reuealed vnto that holy Apoſtle, as likewiſe vnto all the reſt of Gods Prophets and Apoſtles, they haue publikely preached, and plainly left them in writing vnto poſteritie to be ſeene, read, and knowne of all, not onely for their ſakes which are learned, but alſo for their ſakes, which are more ignorant, to bee openly taught and preached vnto them by the ſucceeding Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Wherefore if we the Miniſters of Chriſt wil exſpect, to haue the ſame comfort in our Callings that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:2461:11"/>the reſt of the Apoſtles had, we muſt take the ſame courſe in teaching which they haue done, namely, to publiſh the ſecrees of the Goſpell, that is, all which God hath reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his Word, ſo farre as our knowledge may attayne vnto.</p>
               <p>And truly the confideration of the premiſes, did partly induce my minde at the firſt to determine vpon this Text, and to ſpeake of this finne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, for my Text directing mee to ſpeake of leffer ſinnes, againſt the holy Spirit of God, me thought, (and God I truſt dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted my thoughts) it ſhould be to ſome purpoſe, to ſpeake of the greater or greateſt of all.</p>
               <p>Obſeruing this not by the way, worthy to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, that though the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt may be knowne and is reuealed in the Scripture, yet the Sinner is not eaſily, rather not at all, to be pointed at, nor to bee iudged of men, but to bee left to the iuſt Iudgement of God, one reaſon hereof may be, becauſe finall impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie muſt accompany this ſinne, which cannot eaſily bee diſcerned of men.</p>
               <p>One note more before we enter into the deſcription of this ſinne, would bee obſerued, which a learned man hath well noted, and therefore I will vſe his owne words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Blaſphemia in Spiritum Sanctum, non referri debet, ad Spiritus eſſentiam ſimpliciter, ſed ad gratiam qua donati ſumus:</hi> which is, <hi>That this Blaſphemie againſt the Holy Ghoſt, is not ſimply to bee referred to the Eſſence of Gods Spirit,</hi> (nor to his perſon, for ſo in ſinning againſt the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, wee ſinne in like manner againſt the Father and the Sonne) but it is to bee vnderſtood, that in ſo blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, wee ſinne againſt the good gifts and graces of Gods holy Spirit, wherewith wee haue formerly beene inlightned.</p>
               <p>Now come wee in Godsfeare, to ſpeake of the ſinne it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>What the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt is not, wee haue alreadie partly noted, to wit, That it is not properly not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2461:11"/>onely blaſphemie againſt God the Father, not againſt the Sonne, nor euery Blaſphemie againſt the Holy Ghoſt, as grieuing of Gods Spirit, nor refiſting of Gods Spirit, nor back-ſliding or falling from God and his Truth, through feare, or any other infirmitie; nor perſecuting of Gods Church and Children, through ignorance, neither is it any particular fin committed againſt the firſt or ſecond Table, neither is it final impenitencie, as ſome of the Fathers haue affirmed, for there be thouſands which neuer tru ly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, which neuer yet commit this ſinne.</p>
               <p>Therefore if one ſaith well, <hi>Qui impenitentiam eſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finiunt nullo n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tio refelli poſſunt.</hi> But rather it may bee ſaid to be ſuch a ſinne, which contayneth in ſome ſort, all theſe ſinnes, and more too, becauſe who ſo committeth this ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, ſhall hardly acquit himſelfe of any ſinne; whereunto finall impenitencie muſt be added; before this ſinne can be iudged by man to bee at the higheſt. Now what this peculiar and proper ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt is, ſhall beſt be diſcuſſed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.31.</note> out of the Goſpell where our Sauiour Chriſt ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the Sonne, if wee duly and thorowly confider it as we ſhould: And firſt we muſt note, and well obſerue, who and what manner of perſons they were, to whome our Sauiour obiecteth this ſinne; which is eaſily to bee collected out of the Hiſtorie it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>For there it appeareth, that they were of the worſer ſort of the Phariſies, to whome Chriſt obiecteth this ſin; for when Chriſt Ieſus by his diuine Power, had diſpoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Deuill out of the dumbe man, theſe worſer, I meane, more malicious ſort of the Phariſies, being preſent, pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into his actions, and being by no meanes able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him, yet to the end the people ſhould not beleeue in Chriſt, they coyne a Blaſphemie in the higheſt degree, of meere malice and enuie; and contrarie to their owne knowledge and conſcience, they ſpew out the ſame euen in deſpight of Gods Spirit; ſaying, and affirming with brazen browes, <hi>that Chriſt had caſt out that Deuil,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.24.</note> through
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2461:12"/>Beel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>zebub the chiefe of Deuils,</hi> which curſed calumnie, and moſt ſlanderous Blaſphemie, after that our Sauiour had fully confuted, for the godlies ſake which ſtood by &amp; heard him, hee preſently turneth his ſpeech to thoſe Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, And with ſterne countenance, no doubt, as in ſuch a cauſe was meete, he reprooueth them with a <hi>prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hoc,</hi> for this I ſay vnto you, <hi>Euery ſinne and Blaſphemie ſhall bee forgiuen vnto men, but the Blaſphemie against the Holy Ghost, ſhall not bee forgiuen vnto men,</hi> and with all more ſharply reprooues them, <hi>calling them a generation of Vipers,</hi> as doubtleſſe they were of the vileſt kind.</p>
               <p>And Saint <hi>Marke</hi> in his diſcourſe ſetteth out their ſinne more plainly and fully,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marke</hi> 3.36.</note> ſaying. For they ſaid, Hee, that is, Chriſt, had an vncleane or impure ſpirit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that Euangeliſt would intimate vnto vs, that it was they, Phariſies, that had blaſphemed, and ſo ſinned againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>Howbeit wee muſt obſerue, that our Sauiour Chriſt doth not ſay openly and plainly, though he gaue them ſo much to vnderſtand cloſly by the concluſion of his ſpeech, that theſe Phariſies were ſinners againſt the Holy Ghoſt. By whoſe example we are admoniſhed, as before I haue noted, not raſhly, rather not at all to iudge of ſuch ſinners, howſoeuer the ſinne doe appeare vnto vs what it is, but our Sauiour like a ſound Teacher and skilfull Logitian, plainly putteth downe the maior Propoſition, <hi>What the ſin of the Holy Ghoſt is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The minor they themſelues knew, being conuicted in their own conſciences, that they had committed the ſame ſinne.</p>
               <p>The concluſion therefore followed of courſe, ſuch a ſinne or blaſphemie, ſaith Chriſt, is ſinne againſt the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Choſt;</p>
               <p>Such a ſinne or blaſphemy, ſaith their conſciences, haue we commited;</p>
               <p>Therefore, ſurely, wee haue ſinned againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2461:12"/>Moreouer, we may not forget to note, that theſe filthy Phariſies, were before this time inlightned with ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall beames of Gods Spirit, yea, conuicted in their owne conſciences by former Propheſies, and by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Miracles of Chriſt, concerning the Truth which he taught: yet notwithſtanding, willingly, maliciouſly, and of purpoſe, they did hate the knowne truth, fearing or rather knowing, and ſometimes confeſſing ſo much, that if Chriſt his Truth and Doctrine ſhould be once publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiued, then their Errours and Traditions (like our Popiſh Traditions now) ſhould bee reprooued, their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe and Hipocriſie diſcouered, their credit and gaine diminiſhed, and finally, all their worldly pompe and glorie ſhould vtterly be extinguiſhed, and cleane put out.</p>
               <p>Rather then this ſhould come to paſſe, they will euen oppoſe themſelues <hi>(Gigantum more)</hi> to fight againſt God, and therefore with indurate obſtinacie renounce they the manifeſt truth, and withall their might and malice oppoſe themſelues againſt it, by blaſphemous and ſophiſticall ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilling, and that not ſeruing their turne, by moſt cruell threatnings, excommunicating and perſecuting vnto death, euen Chriſt himſelfe, after him his Apoſtles, as the Prophets before, with many other of Gods deare Saints and Children, profeſſing Gods Truth.</p>
               <p>How neere the practice of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath and doth agree, with the Synagogue of theſe high Prieſts, Scribes and Phariſies, euen a blind man may well ſee and perceiue?</p>
               <p>Vpon all this that hath beene ſaid, and collected out of the Text and courſe of Scripture, where Chriſt intreateth of this ſinne, ioyned with the practice of theſe proud Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies, It ſhall not be ouer-hard to define, what the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt is.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peccatum in Spiritum ſanctum</hi> (ſaith a learned Diuine) <hi>est veluntaria veritatis euidenter cognitae,
<note place="margin">The fin againſt the Holy Ghoſt defined.</note> renunciatio &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellio; ex odio veritatis nata, coniuncta cum tyrannica, ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica, &amp; hypocritica oppugnatione.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2461:13"/>
                  <hi>Sinne againſt the Holy Ghost, is a voluntarie, or wilfull renouncing and rebelling againſt the euident and knowne truth, proceeding from hatred of the ſame truth, ioyned with tyrannicall, ſophiſticall and hypocriticall fighting and ſtriuing againſt the ſame, and againſt the true Profeſſors and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This briefe definition haue I choſen among many other, both for the perſipicuity and plaineneſſe thereof, as alſo for the congruitie and agreement that it hath with that which hath beene before ſpoken of this ſinae.
<note place="margin">They which ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt may be known by foure marks</note>
               </p>
               <p>From which definition wee may obſerue, that they which commit this ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, haue foure ſpeciall markes to be knowne by.</p>
               <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> they haue ſome knowledge of the Truth.</p>
               <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for ſome ſiniſter reſpect or other, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a deadly hatred againſt the ſame Truth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> they willingly renounce and fall from the knowne Truth.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> they ſtriue and fight againſt it, and againſt the conſtant Confeſſors thereof, both with tongue, pen, heart and hand, ſpuing and belching out all Blaſphemies to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praue the Truth, vſing all Hypocriſie and Sophiſtrie to colour their falſhood with, executing all rigor and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie againſt the true Profeſſors thereof, and this they doe with all the deſpight they can againſt that Spirit of grace, which did firſt illumine their mindes with ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, which they had once receiued.</p>
               <p>If any doe thinke that no mortall man, would oner op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf with ſuch deſpight againſt God his Creator, we muſt yeeld that none will or dare ſo to doe, but onely ſuch graceleſſe Caſt-awayes, as through long cuſtome of preſumptuous ſinnings ioyned with double Hypocriſies, haue their hearts hardned, their conſciences ſeared, and themſelues altogether giuen vp into a reprobate ſenſe. For that their ſo greut boldneſſe, cannot but proceed from a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ike blindneſſe, where in malice and poyſonfull furie hath gotten the victorie.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:2461:13"/>Therefore we may ſee, that it is not without great cauſe that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> who was once a Blaſphemer,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</note> but ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, diſtinguiſheth, that his ſinne, from wilfull Blaſphemic, which ſin whoſoeuer doth wittingly and willingly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, ſhall cuermore bee barred from Repentance, becauſe hee deſpiſeth that Spirit of Grace, which ſhould worke Repentance in his heart, turning the Gifts and Graces of God reuealed vnto him, for the ſetting forth of Gods Glorie, euen to the hinderance and ſlander of the ſame; and therefore for this his ſo great obſtinacie and wilfull Blaſphemie, ſhall be puniſhed with moſt wofull and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe miſerie. For he is paſt all hope of recouerie, that tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the onely medicine of his ſauing health, into deadly Poyſon, and being once fallen into this gulfe of Perdition, can neuer be renewed againe by Repentance:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.5.6.</note> as the Holy Ghoſt in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is impoſſible, that they which were once inlightned and haue taſted of the heauenly gifts, and were made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, and haue taſted of the good Word of God</hi> (making mention of taſting ſtill, no eating or good digeſting) <hi>and of the power of the World to come, If they fall away</hi> (ſaith the Text, meaning by falling, finall Apoſtaſie, not falls of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie) <hi>it is impoſſible they ſhould bee renewed by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſeeing they crucifie againe to themſelues the Sonne of God, and make a make of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And after in the tenth Chapter of that Epiſtle, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt ſaith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If any ſinne willingly</hi> (meaning no doubt this ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26.</note> for euery one of vs commit other finnes, willingly and wittingly) <hi>If any ſo ſinne, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth no more ſacrifice for</hi> (ſuch a) <hi>ſinne; but a fearefull looking for of iudgement, and violent fire, which ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure the Aduerſarie.</hi> And forth with the reaſon is yeelded drawne <hi>a minore, ad maius;</hi> &amp; applyed by way of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon. He that deſpiſeth <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, dyeth without mercy of how much ſorer puniſhment. Suppoſe ye, ſhall hee be worthy off, which treadeth vnder foote, the Sonne of God, and counteth the blond of the Teſtament an vnho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2461:14"/>thing, where with he was ſanctified, and doth deſpight the Spirit of Grace? So then to reſolue our ſelues (draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to concluſion) touching this point.</p>
               <p>This ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, muſt bee a generall, voluntarie, totall and finall Apoſtaſie or falling from God, and all goodneſſe, not through any infirmitie or weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but of meere malice and boldneſſe, It is in a word (for I deſire to be vnderſtood of the meaneſt) a froward and wilfull Rebellion, ſtriuing and ſpurning againſt the knowne truth, and euen againſt the knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of him that doth it.</p>
               <p>Howbeit all this (in a ſort) may bee compared but to the roote and ſtemme of this ſinne, the ſap and naturall fruit that it yeeldeth forth, is oftentimes fearefull ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, voluntarie periurie, wilfull blaſphemie, both in word and writing, poyſoned Hypocriſie, withall ſinfull pollution of the fleſh, coupled with moſt tyrannicall crn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie (if there be power ioyned to the will) and finally a helliſh kind of furie, pointing out as it were with the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, from whence this ſinne aſcendeth, and whether ſuch finners muſt deſcend, euen to the bottome of Hell, to their curſed Captaine the Deuill, whom in this point they haue preciſely imitated and followed.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſome draw an example of this ſinne, from the Deuill himſelfe, who albeit, hee knew well enough, that Ieſus was that Chriſt, yet neuer ceaſed with all his might and power to impugne the ſacred Maieſtie of God, together with the Kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt, and as farre forth as he could ſought vtterly to ſupplant the ſame,</p>
               <p>Whoſe ſteps and traces theſe Phariſies which blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Chriſt, did directly tread on, vpon the ſent or ſauour thereof our Popiſh Phariſies, and Phariſaicall Papiſts haue moſt kindly hunted, not onely to the vtter perdition of their owne ſoules, but alſo by their ſinfull perſwaſions, and tyrannous compulſions, they haue and ſtill doe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with all their might, to draw thouſands of ſoules with them vnto Hell.</p>
               <p>For how many multitudes of people ſince Poperie firſt
<pb facs="tcp:2461:14"/>began, and fithence that Myſterie of Iniquitie was firſt hatched, they haue cauſed by tyrannie to abiure and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the knowne truth, contrarie to their knowledge and conſciences, is moſt apparantly to bee prooued, and more lamentable to bee read in the ſeuerall Hiſtor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of many particular Nations.</p>
               <p>Of whome I meane of ſuch as haue abiured, through Popiſh tyrannie, we ought to hope well, ſeeing they fell backe of feare not of malice, and therefore there ſinne was not the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding the malicious crueltie of ſo cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a crue, is neuertheleſſe to bee deteſted, becauſe they doe as much as in them lyeth, indeuour not onely to draw ſuch ſilly ſoules into that ſinke of ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, wherein them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are plunged, but alſo into the ſame damnation, wherin they ſhall be for euermore tormented or puniſhed.</p>
               <p>Neither is their Deuilliſh dealing euen in one point (which I will briefly touch) to bee paſſed ouer in ſilence, namely that when theſe Popiſh Perſecutors, either through perſwaſion and faire promiſes, either through ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor and threatnings, they had cauſed, <hi>(O curſed cauſers)</hi> many poore ſoules to denie with their tongues the Truth of their Sauiour, and being thereupon eſcaped their hands, haue confeſſed Chriſt againe, according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and meaning of their mindes, <hi>Theſe greedie Woolues haue ſoone caught againe thoſe ſimple Lambs, and after they haue compelled them by a new kind of tyranny, the ſecond time to abiure, haue preſently (they being in ſuch lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble caſe) condemned them for relapſe as they call it, to bee most cruelly burned, meaning therby (for what other meaning could they haue) to ſend them through the fierie torments of this life, to the flaming fire that burneth for euer in Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the tender Mercies of our good God, through the rich Merits of their Sauiour, in whom they might beleeue, and for their ſinnes repent; did pardon (I hope) the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their ſin committed, no doubt) through feare and humane infirmitie; and the ſame God (I feare) hath or will double requite their puniſhment vpon the heads of
<pb facs="tcp:2461:15"/>thoſe peſtilent peſecutors, who ſought not outly the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of their bloud, but the vtter damnation of their ſoules and bodies for euermore.</p>
               <p>So that now to conclude with the time (with heartie thankes alſo vnto God, for inabling me thus farre, and to you (reuerend and worthy Auditorie) for your patience in hearing mee hitherunto) It is I truſt very apparant, with what Helliſh Furies they are poſſeſſed, which are the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of Gods Church and Children, who if they haue once taſted and confeſſed Gods Truth, and be after Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of the ſame Truth and the Profeſſors thereof; as <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> the Apoſtata, and many other haue beene, they ſhall neuer be able to acquit themſelues of this ſinue againſt the Holy Ghoſt, nor ſhall euer be forgiuen thereof, but eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſhall be puniſhed in the flames of Hell.</p>
               <p>And ſo much for that ſinne, and the puniſhment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Now let vs all prayſe God, for that which hath beene ſpoken at this time, and pray wee his diuine Maieſtie for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, to giue vs a true feeling of the ſame, and grace to auoyd thoſe ſinnes we haue ſpoken off.</p>
               <p>That we his Children, may not henceforth as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore grieue the holy Spirit of God, by our ſinfull and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe liuing. That the wicked alſo who are not yet effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called, may now at the laſt, yeeld obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto Gods mercifull calling, and no longer to reſiſt the holy Spirit of God, which daily together with the preaching his Word calleth them vnto Repentance.</p>
               <p>And finally that none may euer bee giuen ouer into ſo reprobate a fenſe, as to fall into ſmall Apoſtaſie, and ſo to commit that great finne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, neuer to be forginen. Now to God our heauenly Father, who in his Wiſedome hath created vs. To God the Sonne who in great Mercie redeemed vs. To God the Holy Ghoſt who laboureth continually to ſanctifie vs.</p>
               <p>To God I ſay, immort all, inuiſible, and onely wiſe, bee rendred of vs and all Saints and Angels in Heauen &amp; Earth, all Honour, Glorie, Prayſe, Power and Maieſtie through Chriſt Ieſus, from age to age, and in all Eternitie.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2461:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
